Guide to the John Metcalf Garfield Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Metcalf Garfield papers
1812-1872
MS 968
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
Half of the papers consist of a diary (1815-1816) and notes kept while Garfield was a student at Yale University. Later material documents his activities as a teacher and as a clergyman. Included are notes on sermons, on classical literature, account books, a record of baptism, marriages and funerals (1826-1872), and papers on the New Haven Female Seminary and the Albany Female Seminary. Also included is the account book (1821-1825) of his wife, Ann Lyon Garfield.
Garfield, John Metcalf, 1790-1872
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1940.
Scope and Contents
The papers of John Metcalf Garfield consist primarily of diaries, notebooks, and account books. There is, first, a series of five notebooks recording expenses and lectures at Yale College, 1812-1816. In two of these are included diary entries for the years 1815-1816 and 1823-1825, while a separate volume continues the diary combined with Garfield's ecclesiatical itinerary for 1826-1828 and a record of baptisms, marriages, and funerals for 1826 to 1872. Notes on sermons and Greek literature conclude this series of notebooks.
The next group of volumes contains records of Garfield's teaching from 1816 through 1830, both of private students and in the New Haven Female Seminary, which he founded in 1819. Included are accounts, grades, and other records. There are also a few items from the Albany Female Seminary.
The final two items in the collection are a lease from Garfield to Robert Morrison for property in New Haven, and a household account books kept by Garfield's wife, Ann (Lyon) Garfield (d. 1872).
The papers are described in greater detail on the following pages. They were purchased in 1940.
Biographical / Historical
JOHN METCALF GARFIELD, eldest son of Timothy and Eunice (Pond) Garfield, was born 21 July, 1790, in Grafton, Mass.
After graduation from Yale in 1816 he began the study of law with Seth P. Staples of New Haven. At the close of his second year, he became a teacher in the Lansingburgh (N. Y.) Academy, and after a year spent there, took charge of the Grammar School in Troy, N. Y.
In 1819 he established a Female Seminary in New Haven, which he conducted successfully until 1831, where he was appointed Principal of the Albany Female Seminary. During this time he pursued theological studies, and was ordained deacon in the Prot. Episc. Church by Bishop Brownell, in Hamden, Conn., 11 Aug., 1822, and was admitted to the priesthood, by the same prelate, in Meriden, 4 June, 1823. From this time he regularly officiated in neighboring towns until his removal from the State.
Mr. Garfield continued in his position in Albany until 1849, when he returned to New Haven. Here he resided until his death, and for the greater part of the time had charge of a church of colored people in the city.
He married, 22 Nov., 1816, Ann, eldest daughter of Nathaniel Lyon, of New Haven, and had two sons and six daughters. He died 10 March, 1872, and his wife two days later.
( Yale University Obituary Record, 1860-1879, page 49)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Education; Spouses of clergy; Women -- Education; Account books; Diaries; Clergy; Educators; Garfield, Ann Lyon, d. 1872; Garfield, John Metcalf, 1790-1872; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1816; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1812-1872; 10"(2 boxes)
  - John Metcalf Garfield
    - Notebook consisting of expenses at Yale College, Oct. 15, 1812-Nov, 22, 1814; notes on Mr. Rutlege's sermon [n.p., n.d.]; rules for Latin accent; simple equations in Algebra; rules for Latin grammar, 1812-1814 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes on Jeremiah Day's lectures in natural philosophy [1814-1815; 67p. nump. through p. 51], followed by notes on two sermons by Rev. Benjamin Hale at Geneva, N.Y., Feb. 19, 1843 [3 p.]. In inverse order on the volume: "Continuation of President Dwight['s] Lectures", July 5, 6, 1816, and "President Dwight's Farewell Address to the Senior Class, July, 1815" [21 p.]; notes on services attended in Albany, N.Y., 1842-1843, mainly sermons of Rev. Horatio Potter, with two by Rev. Alonzo Potter, and one each by Rev. William E. Sprague and Rev. John Williams, [1814]-1816, 1842-1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes on President Dwight's lectures, Mar. 2, 1816-July 2, 1816 [219 p.]; in verso, notes on Professor Day's lectures, Mar. 2-June 8, 1816 [27 p.], preceded by 4 p. on divorce and on a sermon by Rev. Mr. Fay (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes from the Mineralogical lectures of Benjamin Silliman, 1815-1816 [23 p. through 7th lectures, with 11 p. more, beginning with lectures 19, after 32 p. of dairy in inverse order]; written in inverse order, a discourse on sympathy [10 p.], followed by his diary, 1823-1825, 1815-1816, 1823-1825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dairy, May 9, 1815-Jan. 25, 1816; copy of A.L. to unnamed correspondent [n.p., n.d]; notes on Dr. Romeyn's sermon at Lansingburgh [N.Y., n.d.]; 1 p. of accounts, Nov. 24, 1815-Dec. 27, 1819, 1815-1816 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dairy of ecclesiastical itinerary, Jan, 1826-July 19, 1828, followed by record of baptisms, marriages, and funerals, Jan. 1826-Feb. 1872, 1826-1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notes from Bishop Pearson on Faith [54 l. numb. through 40, nearly all written on both sides]; followed by notes on sermons preached in New Haven by Rev. John Seely Stone, 1830-1831 [20 unnumb. p.]; notes on Homer's Odyssey and Sophocles' OEdipus Tyrannus[latter in inverse order], probably by Narthaniel L. Garfield at Albany Academy (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Notes, or parts of sermons, on various biblical texts [penciled notes of 82 unnumb. p., some pinned together; n.p., n.d.; one written on verso of a printed prospectus of "The Academician", [n.d.], undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Accounts with students taught privately in New Haven and later in the New Haven Female Seminary, 1816-1824 [119 p.] with name index to same; followed by 2 sermons at St. Peter's Protestant, Episcopal Chruch [Albany, N.Y.], July 4, 11, 1847 [20 p.]; at end of volume, summary of school accounts, [n.d.]-1822, 1816-1824, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Accounts against students in the New Haven Female Seminary, 1824-1830; catalogue, 1843, of a library and rules governing its use; copies, in a different hand, of verses, 1824-1830, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Grades, ratings, and other records of his students on the New Haven Female Seminary, 1823-1830 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Copy of a bill to Eleaser Gorham for tuition, books and contingences for one pupil in the New Haven Female Seminary, Summer term, 1829; memorandum of amounts due from others on verso (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Albany Female Seminary: order of exercises; report card of Anna Layton, 1834, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - A lease to Robert Morrison of property in New Haven, Connecticut. Signed by both parties to the lease, Mar. 12, 1859, with a later undated agreement on verso. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ann (Lyon) Garfield
    - Accounts and memoranda on nurses, servants' hire, dressmaking, etc., [New Haven, Conn.], 1821-1825 (Box 2, Folder 15)